Guide to the Abortion Conversation Project Records, 2000-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Abortion Conversation Project records 2000-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Abortion Conversation Project.
2.2 linear feet Extent: 1600 Items
The Abortion Conversation Project was founded in 2000 to create strategies to challenge the stigma surrounding abortion. ACP was originally conceived as the 501(c)(3) sister to the National Coalition for Abortion Providers, a lobbying and trade organization for independent abortion providers. In July 2008, both organizations joined forces to form the Abortion Care Network. General administrative, financial, programmatic, and educational records; correspondence; founding documents; records of the board of directors; and files from Peg Johnston, co-founder of the Abortion Conversation Project. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
RL.00008
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Abortion Conversation Project Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2011.
Historical Note
The Abortion Conversation Project was founded in 2000 to create strategies to challenge the stigma surrounding abortion. ACP was originally conceived as the 501(c)(3) sister to the National Coalition for Abortion Providers, a lobbying and trade organization for independent abortion providers. In July of 2008, both organizations joined forces to form the Abortion Care Network, a 501(c)(3) not for profit that expanded the abortion care community around independent providers and harnessed the energy generated by our "open and honest" conversations.
In the first 8 years of its existence, ACP created several initiatives that addressed abortion stigma. With the co-sponsorship of Exhale, it brought together researchers, mental health professionals, clergy, and providers to create an agenda to promote post abortion emotional health. ACP collaborated with the Religious Coalition of Reproductive Choice to develop a curriculum on reproductive loss for their clergy training program. ACP also distributed the workbook, A Guide to Emotional and Spiritual Resolution After an Abortion for the Pregnancy Options Workbooks.
Another initiative was the Mom, Dad I'm Pregnant project which resulted in a website (www.momdadimpregnant.org) and two handouts, one for parents and one for the young people involved in an unintended pregnancy. Similarly, ACP worked with the creators of www.menandabortion.com to create a handout called Especially for Men.
The Abortion Conversation Project sponsored Abortion Conversations in Texas, Florida, and the Northwest (2005-2007) in an effort to create a space where providers and pro-choice allies, including clergy, activists, academics, students, and health professionals, could come together to talk openly and honestly about abortion.
The Abortion and Spirituality Working Group brought together clergy and abortion counselors to explore training aids, handouts, and strategies to assist women with spiritual concerns about an abortion experience.
More information can be found on the Abortion Conversation Project website.
Collection Overview
Collection includes general administrative, financial, programmatic, and educational records; correspondence; founding documents; records of the board of directors; and files from Peg Johnston, co-founder of the Abortion Conversation Project. Acquired as part of the Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture.
Subject Headings
Johnston, Margaret (Peg).; Abortion Conversation Project; Abortion Care Network; National Coalition of Abortion Providers; Abortion services; Abortion counseling; Pro-life movement -- United States; Pro-choice movement -- United States; Abortion -- Law and legislation; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
Related Material
The Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture at Duke also holds the records of the National Coalition of Abortion Providers and the Abortion Care Network, as well as the personal papers of Peg Johnston, a founding member of these groups.
Contents of Collection
- Abortion Conversation Project Records, 2000-2008 and undated, (5 boxes)
  - Abortion Conversation Project articles (Box 1)
  - Board member biographies (Box 1)
  - Board meeting minutes, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - ACP College Conversations (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 2004-2008 (Box 1)
  - Educational material (Box 1)
  - Ephemera (Box 1)
  - Exhale Workshop, 2008 (Box 1)
  - Financial documents, 2005-2007 (Box 1)
  - Florida Abortion Conversation, 2006 (Box 1)
  - Foundation grant proposals, 2000-2006 (Box 1)
  - Handouts for patients (Box 1)
  - Handouts for providers (Box 1)
  - Media project, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Meeting agendas and notes, 2007-2008 (Box 1)
  - NCAP presentation, 2004 (Box 1)
  - Northwest Abortion Conversations, 2007 (Box 1)
  - Online Discussion Project, 2004-2005 (Box 1)
  - Our Truths/Nuestras Verdades (Box 1)
  - Programs, 2004-2005 (Box 1)
  - Margaret (Peg) Johnston's notebook, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Program director search, 2005-2006 (Box 2)
  - Provider to Provider Information, undated (Box 2)
  - Regional Abortion Conversation: Organizer's Guide, 2007 (Box 2)
  - Reports, 2003-2006 and undated (Box 2)
  - Spirituality and Abortion Workshop, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Strategic communications plan, 2005 (Box 2)
  - The Texas Abortion Conversation, 2005 (Box 2)
  - United Informational Front (Box 2)
  - Web design proposals (Box 2)
  - Writings and meeting materials (Box 2)
  - Abortion and Spirituality (Box 3)
  - Proposed Abortion and Spirituality packet (Box 3)
  - Abortion in Translation (Box 3)
  - Accounting (Box 3)
  - Austin Conversation, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Board of Directors (Box 3)
  - Board minutes, 2003-2005 (Box 3)
  - ChoiceLink Up Perspectives (Box 3)
  - Communications Plan, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Compton Grant, 2007 (Box 3)
  - Danco Laboratories, 2005 (Box 3)
  - Diana Foundation (Box 3)
  - En Route, 2004 (Box 3)
  - Financial statements, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Florida Abortion Convention (Box 3)
  - Grant activity, 2002-2006 (Box 4)
  - Gund Foundation, 2006 (Box 4)
  - Invoices, 2004-2007 (Box 4)
  - National Abortion Clinic Directory (Box 4)
  - Northwest Abortion Conversation Project, 2007 (Box 4)
  - Online course, July 2005 (Box 4)
  - Open Meadows, 2005 (Box 4)
  - Our Truths zine, 2005 (Box 4)
  - Patient letters, 2000-2004 (Box 4)
  - Report: Post-Abortion Emotional Health, 2004 (Box 4)
  - Vitriol Grant Proposal, 2006 (Box 4)
  - Tax documents, 2000-2008, (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - Texas Abortion Conversation, 2005, (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - Third Wave Foundation, 2005 (Box 5)
  - Valentine Foundation, 2004 (Box 5)
  - Work plan, 2006 (Box 5)